okay so now let's start with the
specification API so in the criteria API
there are two major issues one is code
duplicity okay and another is there are
lot of code boiler plate let me explain
you
like code duplicity how it is so if you
see this your criteria API which we are
writing we are writing here predicate
right we are creating a predicate it is
nothing but a condition in the we Clause
it is possible that same condition can
be present at multiple methods multiple
classes so the same predicate is reused
at multiple not reused like duplicated
at multiple
places okay so that is one of the issue
with the criteria API they are like
there are lot of duplicate code can be
present in the form of this predicates
the same conditions can be presented
multiple
methods okay and currently I have only
one predicate but let's say that this
method itself let's say have five
predicate and those five predicates
might be used in different 50 or
hundreds of methods different so there
are lot of code
duplicate so the first challenge which
resolves by a specification in API is
code
duplicity the Second Challenge is which
I told code boiler plate if you again
see your code of the the criteria API
you will see so many like criteria you
have to create criteria Builder you have
to create criteria query you have to add
it into from close you have to add it
into the we Clause you have added into
the like typed query pag generation and
then ultimately run it so this is all
known as boiler clo which like all your
business logic is that what are the
conditions which you want to add like
from which table you want to F the data
do you want any join or not and what are
the wear Clauses that's all you are
interested in but which objects to be
create criteria Builder criteria query
how to set it that is not your business
logic right so this is known as code
boiler plate extra code you have to
write to make your functionality run so
with specification API that is also
removed we'll go one by one let's see
that how the code duplicity can be
removed from specification API
so if you see the specification
interface this specification interface
has only one abstract method which is
two predicate it has another method but
it has its
implementation so this um functional
interface or interface which has only
one abstract method is generally known
as functional interface okay so we have
to provide an implementation for
this let's see that it would get clear
how we have to use the two predicate
method to remove the code
duplicity the first step is we have to
create a new class user specification
class and in this class we have to write
a method like each method is generally
considered as one condition one
predicate okay if you have 10 predicate
which you are thinking to add in your
like query you can write for this entity
user user detail entity you can write
all the predicates here so my one
condition is like one predicate here is
phone equals to like whatever the phone
number comes so I have written like
equals phone you can give anything
whatever the phone number is coming and
here like the same thing which we were
doing in criteria AP right CB do equals
like root is like whatever your first
table name the phone and the phone
number this will ultimately return your
predicate okay and I using a Lambda
expression like if you don't know how to
use a Lambda expression and functional
interface how they tied up together so
at the top you will get a link in the
like I have covered in depth about the
functional interface Lambda expression
if you have any doubt with this one how
it is working kindly have a look at once
otherwise you will find little bit
difficult uh like how it is actually
working so the first step which we have
done done is we have created a class and
each method we have provided a Lambda
expression and in this Lambda expression
like it is
expecting whatever the abstract method
is it would accept this three parameter
and once the three parameter is accepted
it has to do this so here I'm doing
nothing but a equals condition what we
were doing in
criteria now I how to use it now in the
service class let's say similarly what
we are doing in criteria API first
created an object of criteria Builder
second created a criteria query and each
row would look like this like I am
getting all the row all the fields of uh
this uh
table I have added a from clause this is
my first table like from this table this
is considered as root select all The
Columns of this root table now the for
the predicate now you see that I remove
that predicate from here and I'm just
invoking a
method so here I have first user
specification dot equals phone number so
I am so this since this is static I am
directly using class dot equals phone
and whatever the phone number which is
coming
so I got this
specification now I will use this to
call the two predicate method this one
and this predicate method accept this
three parameter user root whatever the
first table criteria and the criteria
Builder okay with that this function
will get implemented because it's a
Lambda expression we have provided for
it a specification to predicate so it
will now return me the predicate and it
will come here again if you are not sure
how this is working kindly have a look
at the functional interface and Lambda
expression once link might be coming at
top
right now here if you see that if there
are more methods which I want to use the
same predicate now they don't have to
write it on they just invoke
it okay and rest of everything is same
like how we are using in criteria API so
one thing we have resolved is code
duplicity
right by removing the predicate from the
method to a separate method in a
separate class and that method can be
used by different methods from different
places in the
code okay so we are use nothing but an
specification API okay it's abstract
method to predicate and implementation
we have provided in a separate class
itself okay so very very
straightforward the second problem which
we have is with the code boiler plate
again I told you that there are so many
things which we have to create an object
just to write it which is considered as
a code boiler PL plate so with the
specification we can remove it by using
jpa specification
executor so jpa specific specification
executor has multiple methods which we
can use like find one find all exist and
if you open any one of the method and
see its implementation
you will see that it is doing everything
for us so here it's I'm showing you the
framework code find all get query so if
you go inside this it is creating a
criteria Builder it is creating a
criteria query then it is creating a
from Clause it is creating a predicate
it is creating a we Clause ultimately it
is doing get
result right everything it is doing so
all we have to tell like from
from which table if there is a join join
with what what all the
predicates I have to add it into the
query that's all and everything object
creation is done by
it so how to use it so there this is the
step so first is in the repository we
have to extend jpa specification
executor it will still be empty now
since we have send our repository class
with the repository interface with jpa
specification executor this internally
has all this methods we can use it
directly so we don't have to like
implement it anything this is first
thing second thing create a new class
write all the predicate which you have
to write we have created all the methods
or predicates now one thing you have
understand one thing that specification
is generally for predication predicate
conditions only
okay so here you can say that this is a
kind of hack where I am writing a join
address where I have updated my root
with the join what we were doing but I
returning null I don't want any
conditions here okay so we can do that
and I don't want any condition but I
have updated do a join here okay so that
is uh you can extend the functionality
okay if in future you want to do join
and then you can reuse this
method now in this method of
specification you see that it is look
very simpler than what criteria API
looks
like so I am calling user detail
repository find all and passing the
specification which I'm creating here so
I want like a specification do where
okay now I'm just telling like you
create an object you fetch whatever you
want to fetch the data from tables now
I'm just giving you the conditions
predicates where this is your first
predicate join address so in join
address are we doing anything no we are
returning null me no condition but we
have extended the join F functionality
with the root okay so where the first
predicate where we have done the joining
okay then I am doing an an and operation
with the second predicate equals phone
this is my second and then I am doing
and like name AA this one added third so
I got one specification that I am
passing to result so now here if you see
the code okay I am doing find
all and I'm passing this result how it
will work so see this one first go
inside where it has properly check if it
is null don't do anything okay don't do
anything then the second is
end now end has this logic properly that
it has to resolve the left predicate and
the right predicate so it can go in
recursion also okay after resolving
it then it will goes to the another end
then it will goes to First this
predicate and that pricate left and
right the
framework will create an object it will
create an criteria Builder criteria
query like everything it will create
okay so here this predicate right here
it will ultimately get
resolved through your this methods
whatever the predicates you are writing
and since we are doing this and right
and predicate and all so it
automatically resolve like solve left
solve right solve left solve right so
this ultimately would be get called to
resolve like equals like name and all
those things it will get involved
properly okay so try to debug it try to
implement it then you will realize that
like okay specification API is nothing
different than criteria API it's just
like solving this two functionality if
you compare with the criteria
API here if you see lot of boiler plate
and duplicacy has been removed now we
are just doing this and it is very easy
to understand specification. where
condition one condition two condition
three yeah one challenge is there that
uh if you want to do join and all there
is no direct method available so that's
why we are currently doing hack here
that whatever the root will come we are
updated in but no
predicates right no condition I want to
add or you can do also that 1 equals to
1 something generally we don't do that
uh CB do conjunction CB do conjestion is
the method which do 1 equals to one
generally we don't say that see just
pass null jpa framework will take care
that it won't do anything for
it okay but generally specification is
for predicates conditions only write
condition as much as you can okay and
you just pass the condition
specification to the find all it will
replace all the predicates uh
internally but it will always be
like here if you see always like select
all the rows right will return like if
it is not a page get get return list if
it is a pageable it will return up a
specific page if you are clear with the
functional interface and Lambda
expression again this become very very
simple to you specification
API okay if you have any doubt let me
know we can discuss further uh but I
think with this one jpa is totally
complete okay guys thank you bye